<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Azure on theAutomationDude</title>
    <link>https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/tags/azure/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Azure on theAutomationDude</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 15:30:22 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/tags/azure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>VSCode productivity features and keyboard shortcuts</title>
      <link>https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/posts/vscodeproductivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 15:30:22 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/posts/vscodeproductivity/</guid>
      <description>When you get used to VSCode you will experience a boos to your productivity. Some repetitive tasks when writing code are drastically reduced, with language support, intellisense and more, you don&amp;rsquo;t even need to remember the syntax very well. Keyboard shortcuts is another important feature when coding, since you don&amp;rsquo;t want to take your hands off the keyboard to use the mouse too often.
Keyboard Shortcuts There is a keyboard shortcuts reference as https://code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting up and ready with VSCode</title>
      <link>https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/posts/gettingupandreadywithvscode/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 09:48:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/posts/gettingupandreadywithvscode/</guid>
      <description>When you are authoring or editing any type of code or markdown text, VSCode can be a powerfull ally. It will give you syntaxt highlighting and intellisense for most modern programming languages and there is a wide set of extensions to make your life easier. If that wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough, VSCode also has built-in support for Git, meaning that you don&amp;rsquo;t need to learn all the Git commandline syntax and you get a visualization of your branches, commits, staged changes and stash.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How setup Powershell for Azure</title>
      <link>https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/posts/setupazpowershell/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 17:22:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/posts/setupazpowershell/</guid>
      <description>If you are using the Azure Cloud shell, you already have a useful powershell environment setup for you there by Microsoft&amp;hellip;
But it&amp;rsquo;s not that unusual that employers want to keep all your code in a repo that is company controlled and where your teammates can access your files, and that repo may not always be directly accessible from the cloud shell.
For that purpose, you might want to setup your own Powershell environment on the computer you work from.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are the reasons for cloud adoption?</title>
      <link>https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/posts/whycloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 12:22:08 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theautomationdude.github.io/blog/posts/whycloud/</guid>
      <description>The truth is, there are many reasons to use a cloud service, and the priority of those reasons will vary from case to case. But it&amp;rsquo;s important to know these reasons, and how you prioritize them, since they are the drivers of the cloud journey. By understanding which reasons that are most important to your mission, it will help your decision-making process.
Some examples of decisions impacted by these drivers:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
